Finding aid for Nelly Schargo Hoyt papers CA.MS.00061
Smith College Archives
Nelly Schargo Hoyt papers
1937-1993
Smith College Archives
Hoyt, Nellie "Nelly" Schargo, 1920-
CA.MS.00061
4.583 linear feet (6 containers)
The Nelly Schargo Hoyt papers contain class materials, notes, alumnae college sessions, student projects, correspondence, writings, personal documents, and photographs related to Professor Hoyt.
Biographical / Historical
Nelly Schargo Hoyt was born January 15th, 1920, in Nicolaeff, Russia. Her parents, Simon and Vera (Rivkind) Schargo were both educated people. Her father attended Leningrad University and her mother attended St. Olga University in Kiev. Hoyt was born in the aftermath of WWI and the Russian Revolution. In 1922, her father made some criticisms of the local government that angered government officials and ultimately led to his family moving to Berlin.
Hoyt lived in Berlin for several years, and then moved to France, for her secondary education. In Paris, she attended high school, danced with Les Ballets de Jeunesse, and studied anthropology at the University of Paris. At the beginning of WWII, she worked at the Musee de l'Homme. She and her parents fled France and emigrated to New York. In 1941, after two years at the University of Paris, Hoyt was offered the Harriet Boyd Hawes Scholarship, and attended Smith College, graduating magna cum laude in 1943.
Upon graduating from Smith College, Hoyt attended Columbia University where she was a University Fellow. She earned her MA in History in 1944, and her Ph D in 1946. During this time, she worked with such people as Ruth Benedict and Margaret Mead. After graduation, Hoyt stayed in New York City where she worked as a reference analyst for the United States Mission to the United Nations. While she was in New York, she met Nathaniel Deming Hoyt, a professor of education at Columbia University. They were married September 7th, 1946. They had a daughter, Susan, in 1948, and their son, Victor was born in 1958.
During a 1949 trip to Northampton to show her husband the area, Hoyt was offered a one-year teaching position in the History Department at Smith and thus began her 40+ year career. Hoyt was an instructor in history until 1955, an assistant professor until 1960, and an associate professor until 1964, when she was made a full professor. In 1974, Hoyt was named Achilles Professor. As a professor, Hoyt enjoyed combining various fields of study for classes and Alumnae College, which she was in charge of for several years. Some of the courses she taught at Smith included "History, Historians, and Meaning in History," "Time in Space," "Intellectual History of Europe in the 18th Century," and "The Encyclopedie and the Enlightenment." She served as the chairperson of the history department between the 1977/78 and 1978/79 academic years. Hoyt was presented with the Faculty Teaching Award at Rally Day in 1989. She retired from Smith in 1990. Professor Hoyt died on September 25, 2015.
Nellie "Nelly" Schargo Hoyt's publications include History in the Encyclopedia, Methode et Interpretation de l'Histoire, The Family in the French Civil Code, and The Image of the Leader in Soviet Folklore.
Scope and Contents
The Nelly Schargo Hoyt papers largely concern her forty-one years as a professor at Smith College. Most of the collection is made up of class materials, information about the Junior Year in Hamburg program, and notes on symposiums, Alumnae college sessions, and student projects in which she was involved. Also contained in the collection are drafts of various writings, correspondence, personal documents and photographs.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into eight series:
I. Symposiums, Alumnae College, and Student Projects
II. Junior Year in Hamburg
III. Course Materials
IV. Student Theses
V. Trips with the Alumnae Association
VI. Interterm
VII. Personal
VIII. Miscellaneous Materials
Conditions Governing Access
The papers are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source unknown
Hoyt, Nellie Schargo, 1920-; Smith College--Faculty.
- Series I. Symposiums, Alumnae College & Student Projects, 1961-1981
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains information about Hoyt's involvement with various symposiums, Alumnae College sessions and student projects. A little less than half of this series is notes about the "Ladies of the Faculty" Project that Hoyt helped students research and prepare. The information in this series is filed chronologically. Some files in this series are in French.
  - "1761: The Year Revisited", Apr-May 1961 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "L'Anné 1778", 12/12/1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Thomas Couture and the Painting of History" 4/13-6/6 1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "The Diaghilev Years", 1/13-15/1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Mozart Symposiums, undated (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Alumnae College Lectures, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "An Invitation to Versailles", 1970 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Magic", 1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Programs for Various Lectures (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Ladies of the Faculty", 1986-87 (Box 1, Folder 11-17)
- Series II. Junior Year in Hamburg, 1979-1993
  This series is composed of notes and correspondence regarding the Junior Year in Hamburg which Hoyt was in charge for a number of years, as well as her lecture notes and student papers. Some files in this section are in German.
  - Junior Year Abroad, 1979-82 (Box 1, Folder 18-20)
  - JYA General Orientation/Housing, 1990-93 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Hamburg Exchange Program Corr., 1978-82 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Lectures Given in Hamburg, undated (Box 1, Folder 23-4)
  - Copies of Lectures, undated (Box 1, Folder 25-6)
  - Seminar: "Engländer und andere Touristen", 1985 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Seminar Students' Papers, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 28-9)
  - Seminar Students' Papers, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - "Die Reise Nach Utopia", 1982 (Box 2, Folder 31-2)
  - Seminar: Historisches, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Seminar Students' Papers, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 34-5)
  - Miscellaneous German Papers, 1985-6; undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Preparations for Misc. Lectures, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - "Die Suche Nach der Quickseligkeit", undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Enlightenment Bibliography, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Copies: Article Histoire", undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Personal Finances in Hamburg, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Series III. Course Materials, 1956-1990; undated
  This series contains files with notes from classes that Hoyt taught, photocopied readings, and student papers. The files are arranged by course number. Some file in this series are in French.
  - HST 11, undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - HST 30a: Intro to Historical Thought, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - HST 45b: Exoticism in the Encyclopedia, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - HST 100a: La Bruyère on Women, undated (Box 2, Folder 45-6)
  - HST 100b: War & Society 1848-1914, undated (Box 2, Folder 47-8)
  - HST 102b: Personalities in History, undated (Box 2, Folder 49-51)
  - HST 224a: France 1559- French Rev., 1974-5 (Box 2, Folder 52-3)
  - HST 231a: Hist. Of France 1559-1793, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - HST 245b: Age of Monarchy & Rev., 1976 (Box 2, Folder 55-8)
  - HST 246: In Search of Happiness, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 59-62)
  - HST 282a: History, Historians & Meaning, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 63-5)
  - HST 328b: Problems in the French Rev., undated (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - HST 330a, undated (Box 3, Folder 67-8)
  - HST 346b: Voyages Real and Imaginary, 1989-90 (Box 3, Folder 69-75)
  - HST & SS 395: Experience of Exile, 1989-90 (Box 3, Folder 76-9)
  - Misc. Student Papers, undated (Box 3, Folder 80-2)
  - French History Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 83-4)
  - French Revolution Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 85-6)
  - Misc. Photocopied Readings, undated (Box 3, Folder 87-93)
- Series IV. Student Theses, 1956-1990
  This series is a collection of student theses that were written between 1956 and 1990. There is a broad range of topics, but almost all were dedicated to Nelly Hoyt. These files are arranged chronologically.
  - "Initiative and Inception...", 1956 (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - "L'Histoire Vivante and the Fronde", 1965 (Box 3, Folder 95)
  - Le Journal des Scavans, 1680-1715, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 96)
  - "Attitude of French Revolutionaries...", 1965 (Box 4, Folder 97)
  - "From Nantes to Fontainebleau", 1967 (Box 4, Folder 98)
  - "Spectre of Conspiracy During French Rev.", 1978 (Box 4, Folder 99)
  - "A la Gloire du Roi...", 1979 (Box 4, Folder 100)
  - "America from Catesby to Audubon...", 1984 (Box 4, Folder 101)
  - "Musical Expression...", 1987 (Box 4, Folder 102)
  - "Hannah Arendt: Citizen of the World", 1987 (Box 4, Folder 103)
  - "A Questionable Legacy...", 1990 (Box 4, Folder 104)
  - "Educational Policy of Thermidoreans...", undated (Box 4, Folder 105)
- Series V. Trips with the Alumnae Association, 1984; 1988
  This series documents two trips that Hoyt arranged with the Alumnae Association. One, in 1984 was titled "The Baltic World," and the other, which occurred in 1988 was entitled "Dukes of Burgundy, Kings of France." The files in this series are arranged chronologically.
  - The Baltic World, 7/20-8/1 1984 (Box 4, Folder 106-10)
  - Dukes of Burgundy, Kings of France, 5/18-6/2 1988 (Box 4, Folder 111-13)
- Series VI. Interterm, 1978-1979; 1989
  This series is made up of three files containing Hoyt's notes on various interterm projects, in 1978 and 1979. In addition, there is correspondence from the 1989 interterm. The material is arranged chronologically.
  - Teaching of History at Smith College, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 114)
  - The Exuberance of Color, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 115)
  - Correspondence, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 116)
- Series VII. Personal, 1937-1990
  This series contains Nelly Hoyt's personal papers. This series holds a range of materials, including Hoyt's writings and research, items of special interest, family items, and photographs.
  - "A Brief Study of the Peasants' War...", 1943 (Box 4, Folder 117)
  - "Historical Ideas of Diderot...", 1944 (Box 4, Folder 118)
  - Karl May Material, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 119)
  - Strike, 1969-70 (Box 4, Folder 120)
  - Papers of Nicole Hanslick, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 121)
  - Correspondence Received, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 122)
  - Russian Folklore Old and New, undated (Box 4, Folder 123-4)
  - Book Reviews, undated (Box 4, Folder 125)
  - "18th Cen.: The Enlightenment...", undated (Box 4, Folder 126)
  - Europe in the 16th & 17th Centuries, undated (Box 4, Folder 127-8)
  - Europe in the 16th & 17th Centuries, undated (Box 4, Folder 129-30)
  - Drafts of Writings, undated (Box 4, Folder 131)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, undated (Box 4, Folder 132)
  - Photos of Nelly Hoyt, 1937; 1941-3 (Box 4, Folder 133)
  - "Albert Einstein: A Personal Memoir", undated (Box 4, Folder 134)
  - Poems for My Son, Victor, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 135)
  - Photo of Margaret Mead, undated (Box 4, Folder 136)
  - Book: "Lettre d'un Professeur Allemand", undated (Box 4, Folder 137)
- Series VIII. Miscellaneous Materials, 1976-1990; undated
  This series contains miscellaneous papers. These items were placed in this series because they do not contain enough information to be placed otherwise. This section is largely made up of files about Beaumarchais, a French playwright. Some material in this series is in French.
  - Beaumarchais (Box 4, Folder 138-52)
  - Historian in Landscape, undated (Box 4, Folder 153)
  - Feasts, Fools and Carnivals, undated (Box 4, Folder 154-5)
  - Journal des Savantes, undated (Box 4, Folder 156-7)
  - History and Legend, undated (Box 4, Folder 158)
  - Microfiches of French Readings, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 159)
  - Title Pages and Tables of Content, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 160)
  - Bibliographies and Catalogs, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 161)
  - Marc Blanc Information, undated (Box 4, Folder 162)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1988-90 (Box 4, Folder 163)
  - Tronchet Notes and Biographies, undated (Box 4, Folder 164)
  - Personal and miscellaneous papers (Box 5)
  - Ladies of the Faculty class project (Box 6)